hi welcome back to the channel and today
on Polar Ice Creamery we are going to
talk about eggnog what it is and why you
can't just Churn it into ice cream then
we're going to make one that you can
churn into ice cream so stick around and
let's see what it's all
[Music]
about
eggnog there are a million recipes for
eggnog
online and that's probably you know
underestimating there's some notably
good
ones most of them pretty bad but
actually in reality what seems to happen
is is probably five or six
people make their eggnog reasonable
recipes
people take the majority of those
ingredients and then change them to make
their
own just UNT for that those people don't
really know what they're doing so
they're they're taking ingredients from
a good recipe adding a lad of other crap
or taking some mental stuff out and
putting it back out there as their own
recipe and let's let's be fair that's
how new recipes are
created you modify them to your liking
so I guess if you look at it like that
then you know they're fine they're what
they the people that created them wanted
them to be or maybe not but there is
actually some science behind eggnog and
that's what we're going to talk about
today
so what is
[Music]
it Max Miller or tasting history with
Max Miller he did an excellent eggnog
video I'm going to put a link below and
if you're not subscribed to him why not
it amazing content really nice guys so
head over and do the
stuff
now let's assume that you've just
watched that which is probably a good
idea to be
fair come back here and let's talk about
what happens with
[Music]
eggnog
custards that's really what it is it's a
kind of custard it's a type of custard
what what actually is a custard you know
it's a
it's a a viscous liquid made using egg
yolks and dairy traditionally that's
what it is or what it used to
be now you could I guess in modern times
you
could say that custard is just a semi
viscous
liquid move the the NOG out the
way now as ice cream makers we know
custards we we know how to make these
viscous liquids cuz we do it every day
every week if you're if you do this as a
profession then you do nothing but make
those kind of liquids now let's get
storeboughtslime
it's
creamy it's got a nice bit of nutmeg
flavor going through there it's a pretty
decent viscosity so it's relatively
thick but not so thick um some of them
are really
watery you know this this actually isn't
a bad eggnog and you'll find those in
the
stores and if you're happy with that
then great chances are you're not though
cuz that's why you're watching this
video so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to knock up this recipe
here it's one of the most well-reviewed
eggnog recipes online and we're going to
compare it
to this one and for my
eggnog the scientific ice creamer way of
making eggnog what you're going to need
is 300 G of 3% milk 250 g of 33%
whipping cream 60 G of skin milk powder
80 g of sugar 60 G of glucose syrup 40
de de me to deex is equivalent and 100 G
of egg
yolks and that
mixture on an ice cream calculator gives
us 14% fat 11% sugar 11.7 milk solids
nonfat 43.3 total solids
56.7%
water all well within the range of
standard ice cream apart from the sugar
which is actually a bit low but by
including the 40D glucose syrup we are
changing the freezing point enough
hopefully to allow us to not boost the
sweetness too much cuz obviously 4de is
is nowhere near as sweet as sucros it's
40 to 45% the sweetness so it comes out
this recipe with a part 40 is going to
freeze a little harder obviously with
such low sugar but we'll just take it
out what we're trying to do here is
create an
eggnog that is also an ice cream so
let's make it okay here we go onto the
scientific eggnog recipe we're going to
start
with our
sugar straight
in egg yolks straight in and this is our
4de glucose syrup okay so we're just
going to get this out sticky old stuff
you can warm it in a
microwave
for just a few seconds that makes life
much easier but I just like to show you
how sticky things can be here we go
look there we go I actually did two Gams
over cuz I knew I'd get some wastage so
I'm just going to put all that in
there okay now that that's
just loosening up a little bit that glue
are starting to blend in we're going to
just kind to add in our final ingredient
which is our skin milk
powder and up we go to 65 to
70°
Centigrade yeah see about 66 1
12° on average good place to
be we know at that temperature the egg
yolk proteins are doing what they need
to do they going to thicken our liquid
nicely which it's doing
already so obviously the point of the
science based eggnog is to create an
eggnog that we can also turn into ice
scen okay so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to decant enough into here to do
the minimum churn in this machine and
put the rest back in the fridge and once
this is churned we'll load it in a tub
and put it in the freezer so we can
taste it all together at the
end put your vanilla extract in your
custards when they're cool or cold if
you put them in when they're on the hob
like the other recipe actually what
you're doing is you're burning
off that alcohol and that alcohol is
what
is carrying the vanilla flavor
so the more you evaporate of that off
the weaker your vanilla is going to be
so I strongly recommend you put your
extracts in when your mix
is around 50° Centigrade or colder
[Applause]
[Music]
okay
that's so good we got everything out so
we've got the taste better from
scratching here so we're going to get
some of that into this mousse glass can
you see the glasses yes you can let's
just move that back like
that
and the
remaining
science
eggnog I shouldn't really call it
science eggnog I should just call it ice
cream eggnog
maybe okay so I guess first things
first let's dust each
one with just a little
bit let's get the playing field even so
the lucer and the store
boo
it is good it does taste
nice I actually like
this I've probably had three Gardens of
this already and it's only the 16th of
November lovely sunny beautiful snowy
day here in
Alberta and this is
the tastes better from
scratch much
thicker that's
naughty that's
good
nutmeg much much thicker same kind of
smell you know so the
the whatever the fake and artificial
stuff they've got in there along with
the natural stuff it is the same
strength to the nose that the tastes
better from scratch one is but this one
is much thicker much creamier much much
creamier you couldn't drink as much of
this as you could of that and then this
is mine po ice cream
eggnog smells the same you probably
getting you know the nutmeg to the nose
straight away
but now
okay so we got same texture as this one
so it's thick creamy luxurious
lingers but it lingers for much longer
it's still going
now oh that is
good
wow
okay the point of this video was to make
eggnog you can drink that's comparable
to that that you can also turn into an
ice cream so let's get it out of the
freezer not timed I haven't had it out
for 10 minutes then put it back in the
freezer for the last 5 minutes straight
out the
freezer feels okay doesn't feel too
hard that
40D glucose syrup done the
job you you won't be able to see a lot
in there it's just eggnog colored ice
cream let get my get my bowl and Dish
them
[Music]
up all right so let's do the same
thing touch a
kn nog
nutmeg scooped really really well not
too soft not too
[Music]
hard
that is
perfect I don't know what say it it's
perfect it tastes identical to the
eggnog such a good
texture no discernable ice at all which
you would 100% get if you turn that and
that oh that's
good okay well there we go I mean that's
a winner right there if you want to make
an eggnog that you can also churn into a
perfect eggnog ice cream this is the one
here okay if you're going to make eggnog
ice cream you probably could use this
recipe just eat it straight away don't
freeze it because it it it's junk when
you freeze it it's
it's better than that one that one turns
to ice in about half an hour after being
frozen this one turns to ice after about
24 hours and then you just get loads of
ice crystals in there cuz it's it's 25%
too low in solids okay this
one it's perfect and if you don't have
that glucose 4 de
syrup then just I'll do an adjustment
for the recipe but that's what's making
this here so we're not too sweet and
that's that pulling that flavor of the
eggnog straight through if it's too
sweet then all you taste is just sugar
but
perfect thanks for coming with me on
this eggnog journey in
it's being an eye opener anyway thanks
very much for watching don't forget to
like And subscribe and I have also just
opened a patreon account for those that
might be interested I've also got Kofi
as well so if you don't like one or the
other then you got a couple of choices
what I'm also going to do is is I've
listened to the feedback from you lovely
subscribers I'm going to keep the videos
a little bit shorter and put the heavy
science-based ones on patreon so you can
you can watch those there but thanks and
see you next
[Music]
week